<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Seasonable advice to all Protestant people of England heartily recommended by a lover of his countrey.</title>
            <title>Seasonable discourse shewing the necessity of maintaining the established religion in opposition to popery.</title>
            <author>Lloyd, William, 1627-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2692A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24024588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24024588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1705:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Seasonable advice to all Protestant people of England heartily recommended by a lover of his countrey.</title>
                  <title>Seasonable discourse shewing the necessity of maintaining the established religion in opposition to popery.</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, William, 1627-1717.</author>
                  <author>Fell, John, 1625-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally published under title: Seasonable discourse shewing the necessity of maintaining the established religion in opposition to popery--cf NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Variously attributed to Lloyd and Fell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Seaſonable Advice TO ALL Proteſtant People OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Heartily recommended by a Lover of his COUNTREY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109621:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109621:2"/>
            <head>Seaſonable Advice TO ALL Proteſtant People OF ENGLAND. Heartily recommended by a Lover of his COUNTREY.</head>
            <p>I Think there be few men ſo unobſerving as not to ſee, that many are much inclined to ſtand upon their guards, and by Arms (if it appear unlikely to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe done) to ſecure themſelves, and Religion, in ſuch ſort, as may ſeem moſt for their own intereſt, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Truth. Therefore it ſhall be the buſineſs of theſe Papers, to enquire into the Cauſes and Reaſons of ſuch a diſpoſition, together with all Motives and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements thereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, Some conjecture, this is the moſt probable way we can go to work our own intereſt in point of Safety, Trading and Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109621:3"/>To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of conceſſion, That ſome indeed plead a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign War may ſometimes be needful, and therefore bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to a Nation, if ſucceſsfully managed: becauſe it takes away many idle and Vagabond perſons; many Cheats, Thieves and ill Husband, who, like Caterpillars, only live on the fat of the earth, and as drones, or <hi>Lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains,</hi> feed on other mens labours. And alſo as it keeps up a people in the courage, and diſcipline of War. For hereby a Nation is not only eaſed of a burden both charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and troubleſome; but is alſo made the more able to defend her ſelf againſt any foreign Invader. And by the ſame means other Countreys may be made the ſeat of that War, which elſe in little time might have been brought home to their own doors. For by this courſe, the many and great Evils, that Armies generally cauſe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauching of perſons, in illegitimate offsprings, in waſting of goods, and cattel, are all avoided: the things that would have been conſumed by perſons thus employed, are ſaved; and the increaſe of ſuch evil inhabitants migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſtopped, which things ſoon compenſate the charges of an ordinary War.</p>
            <p>But in a Civil War the caſe is wonderfully altered.</p>
            <p>For then all debauches, and illegitimate increaſe, is amongſt our ſelves: then they be our own Shops and Houſes, our own Barns, and Stables, that are plundered: then every Trophy is an argument of our own calamity; and all ſpoils evidence our own loſſes: and every ſlaughter is a miſchief to the whole body, from which ſo many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are cut off and periſhed. Which things neceſſarily make a Nation more poor and weak, and conſequently a more eaſie prey to ſome foreign Aſſailant.</p>
            <p>But certainly <hi>we,</hi> above all others, have cauſe to dread ſuch a conteſt: by reaſon we are made up of ſo many
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109621:3"/>
parties, who are all acted by different Religions and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; and amongſt whom, on every ſide animoſities are mightily heightned by former occurrences. That if once <hi>we</hi> fall to pieces, it is not well to be expected that any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane art, or any thing leſs than a Divine Power, is able to compoſe, and ſet us together. Beſides which, we have dangers from without, <hi>viz.</hi> formidable forces, alwayes ready, and watching opportunity of raiſing their own tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies on our ruines. From all which things we may juſtly fear, that as it hath been the fate of the ſtrongeſt Empires and Kingdoms, to fall by their own hands, when others could not deſtroy them; that the ſame deſtiny may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our differences.</p>
            <p>But in caſe this laſt evil, <hi>viz.</hi> of a foreign force, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ruine, do not happen; Yet look to the end of ſuch a Conteſt, and perhaps we may find ſome reaſon to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that the concomitant miſeries of a War, that is, ſlaughters, plunders, ruine of families, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may prove but the <hi>beginnings of ſorrow.</hi> For, in all probability ſuch reſiſters will be either the Conquerors, or the conquered. For ſince mens Spirits are <hi>now</hi> ſo heated, that a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of differences is ſo difficult, even while peace conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues; when the Sword is once drawn, it may poſſibly appear utterly impoſſible: as when the late King's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions were voted ſatisfactory by ſome, no Conceſſions would ſatisfie others. And let Victory incline either way, reſiſters muſt expect far greater evils than what they now lye under. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If they be overcome, reaſon will not ſuffer us to hope eſcaping the wrath of the Powers reſiſted. And ſo much the rather, becauſe ſuch will not be a ſingle offence, but a repetition of like things ſtill freſh in memory, and which Authority ſo eaſily paſſed over. And though cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are ſo much different from what they were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109621:4"/>
before, that it muſt needs go very hard on their ſides, who may thus ſeek to ſecure themſelves from what they fear: yet becauſe men are much uncapable of receiving impreſſions from Arguments of this nature, by reaſon of their numbers (the very thing that emboldned the <hi>Jews</hi> to enter into a War with the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, whereby they enſured and haſtened the total ruine of their <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> that is, their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> at once) I ſhall therefore (ſince ſuppoſitions grant nothing) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them more likely, than I judge they are, to be the Conquerors. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If ſo, they muſt look to be enſlaved <hi>either</hi> by the Forces which made them Victorious; and then, as the <hi>Romans</hi> once were, be governed by a ſtanding Army, which made Emperours, and ruled in all points according to their own pleaſures; which, if ever it ſo happen, will, like a Band of Robbers, make ſpoil and plunder of all they like; and be ſure will have good Commons, when they be their own carvers:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or</hi> elſe fall under the will and power of ſome cunning head, that ſhall feed the Souldiery with the ſpoil of the people, that by them he may be empowered to act his will upon the Nation. By which means the wealth and treaſure of the Land, ſhall be divided between tyrannical Uſurpers, and the Forces that uphold them.</p>
            <p>If you think this unlikely, reflect a little upon late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters, and you will find, it was the miſery of this Nation, that <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> all went to wrack for the ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating an hungry and ungovernable Army. Of which, a late <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> in his <hi>Iter Boreale</hi> brings in the Nation thus ſighing her complaints,
<q>
                  <l>That I ſhould ſink with Juſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ay accord,</l>
                  <l>Who let my Pilot be thrown over board.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109621:4"/>Yet 'twas not I, ye Righteous Heavens know,</l>
                  <l>The Souldiers in me needs would have it ſo.</l>
               </q>
And a little after he ſpeaks of them, as ſetting up a ſingle Perſon, after the Death of <hi>O. Cr.</hi> of whom thus,
<q>
                  <l>A Legion then he rais'd of armed Sprights,</l>
                  <l>Elves, Goblins, Fairies, Quakers, and New Lights:</l>
                  <l>And with theſe—</l>
                  <l>—he Church and State poſſeſt.</l>
                  <l>Who, though they fill'd all Countreys, Towns, and Rooms,</l>
                  <l>(Yet, like the Fiend, that did frequent the Tombs)</l>
                  <l>Churches, and Church-ground, they haunted moſt,</l>
                  <l>No Chappel was at eaſe from ſome ſuch Ghoſt.</l>
                  <l>The Prieſts, ordain'd to exorciſe thoſe Elves,</l>
                  <l>Were voted Devils, and caſt out themſelves.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bible,</hi> or <hi>Alchoran,</hi> all's one to them,</l>
                  <l>Religion ſerves but for a ſtratagem.</l>
                  <l>The Holy Charms theſe Adders did not heed,</l>
                  <l>Churches themſelves, did Sanctuary need.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after they are dividing the Univerſity Lands among themſelves, and in fine,
<q>
                  <l>—When we have done theſe, we'll not be quiet,</l>
                  <l>Lordſhips, and Land-lords Rents ſhall be our dyet.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For which reaſons men ſorely repented, that they were ever thought to petition they might be put into a poſture of defence: for by this means they became utterly unable to defend their own <hi>Perſons, Eſtates,</hi> or <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do the people really think they may become vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, and that the Army, by which they are made ſo, will not be proud and inſulting? or that the Commanders
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109621:5"/>
will not turn the Victory to their own advantage? Can they think men are become ſo honeſt now, to what they were of late, when all the talk of Reformation ended in the dividing Crown and Church lands, and great mens eſtates amongſt themſelves? Can they expect better deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than then, when the <hi>liberty of the ſubject,</hi> ſo much talk't of, miſerably ſunk into a perfect bondage? Of which the ſame <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> thus,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now broke in <hi>Egypt's</hi> plagues all in a day,</l>
                     <l>And one yet worſe than theirs; we muſt not pray</l>
                     <l>To be deliver'd! There ſcab'd folk were free</l>
                     <l>To ſcratch where it did itch: ſo might not we.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our Magiſtracy was, like <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod,</l>
                     <l>Turn'd to a Serpent by the angry God.</l>
                     <l>Poor Citizens, when Trading would not do,</l>
                     <l>Made Brick without Straw, and were beaten too.</l>
                     <l>Struck with the Botch of Taxes, and Exciſe,</l>
                     <l>Servants, our very duſt, were turn'd to Lice.</l>
                     <l>It was but turning Souldiers, and they need</l>
                     <l>Not work at all, but on their Maſters feed.</l>
                     <l>Strange Caterpillars eat our pleaſant things,</l>
                     <l>And Frogs croak'd in the Chambers of our Kings.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lightning, Hail, Fire and Thunder <hi>Egypt</hi> had,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>England Guns,</hi> Shot and Powder, that's as bad.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And I am ſure that War began with as fair and plauſible pleas, as any can poſſible be in time to come: <hi>viz.</hi> only to <hi>take away the wicked from before the King, that his Throne might be eſtabliſhed; to bring the King to his Parliament:</hi> and with ſolemn engagements to make him <hi>a great</hi> and <hi>glorious Prince:</hi> To <hi>reform Religion,</hi> and to aſcertain the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109621:5"/>
               <hi>liberty of the Subject.</hi> Our concerns were in the hands of the Parliament, and the Army under the Command of perſons we thought we might truſt. But we ſee whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a few running heads, and the power of the Sword did carry things! Alas! even beſide and beyond the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt actors, who were themſelves enſlaved, as well as them, they firſt expoſed. And certainly we muſt expect that another War, alike proſperous in the ſucceſs of the Sword, if any ſuch ſhall ever be, will prove as unſucceſsful in regard of the ends it firſt aimed at; ſo long as the like Policies and Luſts remain in the World. Nothing is more eaſie than for men to ſit ſtill, and frame fine Idea's and Chimera's of Government to themſelves: but nothing more difficult, than to conſtitute a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to them, when the power is in the hands of other men.</p>
            <p>Therefore all that the people are like to gain upon this ſuppoſal of becoming victorious in ſuch a way, is only this, <hi>viz.</hi> the putting their <hi>Perſons, Eſtates, Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> into the hands of fellow ſubjects, who, when they come to Government, are ever more proud, greedy and tyrannical, than thoſe who are born in high places, and on whom the Government devolves by legal and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected deſcents.</p>
            <p>But in caſe this Storm paſs over, we yet ſee another Cloud ariſing, that will moſt certainly break down in Thunder, and Lightnings, and an horrible Tempeſt. For though now all Parties embody, and jointly endeavour to ſhake off Superſtition, and every evil work; yet if they once ſhall be able to do this, they immediately fall to pieces among themſelves, every one endeavouring to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his own way. For it is not the ultimate end of any one Party meerly to eaſe himſelf of the burdens he now is under; this is but the means, and way to his laſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109621:6"/>
which is, every one to eſtabliſh his own methods. Therefore after all the conteſt and buſtles, which we muſt certainly expect among our ſelves, upon the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of ſucceſs, which perhaps may prove deſtructive to the whole, if any one get into the Chair, all the reſt will combine to pluck him out: and if they gain this point, and any one of the reſt crouds in, all the other, together with him pulled out, will again combine to beat down that. By which means nothing but confuſions, and endleſs diſturbances, are like to follow, till all become a ruine to one another.</p>
            <p>Theſe things <hi>de facto</hi> have been ſo: and that they will be ſo again, if ever matters come to that ſtate, is evident beyond all diſpute, from the very Opinions and Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all Parties now combining againſt the Church. For the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> is for a Government by a <hi>Claſſis</hi> or <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and to have all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and things kept ſtrict and tight to their methods. But the <hi>Independent</hi> is really for no Government at all, but would have every one a Biſhop, and Supream in his own Pariſh: and is againſt Epiſcopacy and Presbyterie, not as ſuch, but as they lay a reſtraint upon his own actings. The <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> differs from both. The <hi>Quaker</hi> would have no Law, nor Rule, but the Spirit: And the <hi>Fifth-Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy-man</hi> will endure no Ruler, but King <hi>Jeſus.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would every Party ſpeak his own ſentiments, they muſt own, they will by no means ſit contented in any way but their own. And that their embodying, and joint cryes for Liberty, are only to ſhake the preſent yoak from their neck, that they may be in a capacity of ſtrugling every one for his own way: And that they would not thus combine, were they ſure any one of them to change the preſent eſtabliſhment of Religion for any way but his own. Therefore ſhould the King be pleaſed to paſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109621:6"/>
a Comprehenſive Bill, or grant a boundleſs Liberty to all Proteſtants, it would pleaſe none any farther, than as it layes open the Church, takes off a preſent reſtraint from the people, and gives every Party hopes at laſt to gain its own eſtabliſhment: whence the fore-mentioned Confuſions muſt neceſſarily follow, if men can ever get rid of the preſent eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>But ſome may plead, All this miſchief may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by this, <hi>viz.</hi> That one Party may become too ſtrong for all the reſt, and keep them from being able to make ſuch diſturbances. To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if ſo, no man can divine which Party that may be. For the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> was baited, and utterly beat out by other Parties. And I fear will be leſs able to ſtand than before, by reaſon <hi>Independents</hi> are encreaſed abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, and have gained more from the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> than men imagine; our Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in his Preface to his <hi>Saints Care of Church-Communion,</hi> argues, that a great body of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are of late ſunk into <hi>Independency.</hi> Or if otherwiſe, we have little ground to expect he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve himſelf againſt the joint endeavours of all others. And if we ſhould ever fall under <hi>Independency,</hi> or a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience, can we think the change worth any little part of our pains we are, or may be at? Can we think of being contented in that condition, which of late years was the anguiſh of our ſouls? Can we make that our choice, which not long ſince was our burden? Some men indeed are apt to reach after any thing but what they have, and hope to gather Grapes of Thorns, and Figs of Thiſtles, till they try, and prick their fingers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſhould be uppermoſt, this is no more than he had before, but could not keep it. For truly they are for Government; they talk't, and preach'd, and wrote all they could againſt Liberty; they decryed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109621:7"/>
the forſaking their Church, as an unwarrantable Schiſm: and would ſeverely have bound up all to their own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods: for which cauſe the <hi>Independent</hi> ſpoke him worſe than the <hi>Pope.</hi> For Mr. <hi>Sterry</hi> in a Sermon at <hi>White-Hall, Nov.</hi> 5. 1651. tells us, that our deliverance from <hi>Popery</hi> is not ſo great a mercy, as our deliverance <hi>from the black plots, and bloody powers of the Northern Presbyterie.</hi> For the ſame cauſe the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> diſputed againſt, and the <hi>Quaker</hi> diſturbed him in the Pulpit, and every Party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared more againſt them, than againſt the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and never reſted, till they had worried and run them down. And if it ſhould be in the power of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to give Laws to others; however as a means thereto, they may yield to Indulgence, Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, Liberty, or any thing; they will then lay a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reſtraint upon the tongues of all Sectaries, and ſtop the mouths of error and folly; elſe they loſe the end and fruit of all their care, pains, dangers, prayers, tears, and whatſoever they have done for the ſervice of truth and the Goſpel. They cannot ſuffer that <hi>woman</hi> Jezabel, <hi>which calls her ſelf a Propheteſs, to teach, and to ſeduce</hi>—which was the great ſin of the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> and for which Chriſt ſaid, he had <hi>a few things againſt her,</hi> Revel. 2.20. And if ever they come to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a Rule, and oblige all others to it, every <hi>Sectary</hi> will cry <hi>perſecution,</hi> and never ceaſe, till they have undermined the Church and the Truth, and thrown all again into utter confuſions. Should any man flatter himſelf into expectation of better fruit, if it ever come to tryal, the iſſue will confute, and fool him to his face. What a crop then muſt we expect from the ſeed of Sedition and diſturbance? What an harveſt, when ſo many hands are ſowing Tares among the Wheat? Surely whatever men do hope, this will be the end of all, that they that <hi>ſow the wind, ſhall reap the whirl-wind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109621:7"/>2. Another cauſe or reaſon of mens being diſpoſed to a reſiſtance of the Powers, is this, that they think it is their bounden duty, as it ſeems to make for the glory of God, and propagation of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This indeed hath been the miſtake and fall of many honeſt and well meaning men, and my ſelf formerly have much ſtumbled at it. But I took the courſe which the ingenious <hi>Carteſius</hi> adviſes in order to the finding out any truth, which is this, to ſtrip our ſelves of all former No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Sentiments, or rather of all Opinions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions formerly imbibed, and ſo, as far as is poſſible, to bring our ſelves to doubt of every thing; and then without prejudice or prepoſſeſſion, to apply our ſelves to the conſideration of the point we would underſtand. In this way I came to be fully ſatisfied, that this point of reſiſting lawful Governours, let them be what they will, is a grand and moſt dangerous miſtake, and hath no foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or any the leaſt colour of encouragement from the Goſpel, or any Epiſtles, or part of the New Teſtament. And as every man is bound upon his Salvation, to come to the light, and uſe the beſt means he can to come to the knowledge of the truth: ſo I doubt not, but if any man will lay aſide his prejudices, and ſet himſelf to the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial conſideration of theſe following heads, he will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to this as an undoubted truth, That a reſiſtance of lawful Governours, let the reaſons or inducements be what they will, is no way our duty, nor by any means lawful. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is no Precept of reſiſtance in all the New Teſtament; I never heard the man, that was ſo hardy, as to plead there is: and if any think there is ſuch a Text, let him find and produce it, that we may conſider it. For Mat. 10.34. <hi>I came not to ſend peace, but a ſword,</hi> ſpeaks only an accidental conſequence; an evil proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109621:8"/>
not from the nature of Religion, which breathes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>on earth peace,</hi> and <hi>good will towards men:</hi> but only from the wickedneſs of the world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhews us not what ought to be, but what will be, <hi>viz.</hi> differences upon the account of Religion: as in V. 15. —<hi>a man at variance againſt his Father, and the daughter againſt her Mother.</hi> And <hi>Luke</hi> 22.36.—<hi>he that hath no ſword, let him ſell his garment, and buy one.</hi> Only gave the Diſciples an hint of the dangers and evils, that were now ready to overtake them: and did not in the leaſt authorize them to make the weapons of their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare carnal. This appears undeniably from our Saviours reproof of <hi>Peter,</hi> who could beſt expound his own mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when he cut off <hi>Malchus</hi>'s ear: of which under the next head, which</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shews that we have no example of reſiſtance in all the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>For when <hi>Peter, Matth.</hi> 26.51. took the Sword, and cut off the ear of the High Prieſts ſervant, <hi>Jeſus</hi> heals the wound, and ſaith V. 52. <hi>Put up thy ſword—for all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi> Where the Margin points us to Gen. 9.6. <hi>Whoſo ſheds mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> Thereby aſſerting, that to kill any man, that comes from a lawful authority, to apprehend even the Perſon of Chriſt, is murder. Therefore to kill any ſent from Authority, though (as they think) in defence of the Goſpel, is murder too. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they make Chriſt's Goſpel more worthy of defence, than his perſon, which certainly they will not do, that talk ſo much of <hi>Imputative righteouſneſs,</hi> of the <hi>perſonal excellencies of Chriſt; and the pretiouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> But if any do ſo, yet ſtill there is no example of reſiſting the Powers for defence of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Therefore this inſtance is an inſtance only of <hi>Peter</hi>'s
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109621:8"/>
weakneſs and error; and gave an happy occaſion to let the World underſtand, that no Plea from the <hi>defence of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>propagation of the Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>the glory of God,</hi> can juſtifie a reſiſtance, or excuſe them from murder, who kill any that are in, or come from Authority, in any manner, or to any end whatever. For if <hi>Peter</hi>'s caſe was not juſtifiable, I am ſure none is.</p>
            <p>Now ſome men reject Infant Baptiſm for no other reaſon but this, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is expreſſed in the Goſpel no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or example of any one Infant baptized. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a precept or example is at leaſt as neceſſary in this caſe, as in the other. Therefore ſince there is none, by parity of reaſon a reſiſtance upon the ſame grounds ought to be rejected too. For the matter comes to this point, <hi>viz.</hi> either Infants muſt be received to Baptiſm, though the Goſpel affords no precept nor example that way: or elſe ſuch reſiſtance muſt be rejected, becauſe the Goſpel gives no precept nor example, this way. Elſe men are humorſome, and do not ſquare their opinions and judgements by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; but bend that ſacred Rule to the obliquities of their own humours: or at leaſt uſe, or not uſe it, according as it may ſerve, or not ſerve their own perſwaſions, or reſolves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Goſpel abounds in precepts of obedience to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours ſimply as Governours, and not as ſuch, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to all Governours, whether good or bad. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever diſtinctions are made uſe of to reſtrain obedience on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch, or to ſome Governours, are</p>
            <p n="1">1. Groundleſs and unwarrantable: for God ſaith, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers:</hi> and that there be no powers, but what are <hi>ordained of God.</hi> What warrant then have any to gainſay the Spirit, and plead that ſome are not ordained of God, and that ſome you ought not to be ſubject to? God ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever reſiſts ſhall receive to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109621:9"/>
himſelf damnation:</hi> what reaſon then have any to affirm that ſome reſiſters ſhall not receive damnation? We ought not to bring reſtrictions, and limitations, unleſs truth, or the nature of the thing ſo require: and if it doth ſo in this caſe, where have you that truth? where is it written? produce your warrant, that we may ſee and be inſtructed by it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such diſtinctions, or limitations are as ſerviceable to the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as the <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> For, becauſe there is no Text, that ſaith we may reſiſt, much leſs any that ſet forth for what cauſes or reaſons men may do it, and that conſequently this Doctrine is gathered only from illogical inferences, ſound of words, and miſapplication of Phraſes, therefore there is no Text, that ever was, or may be pleaded, for ſuch reſiſtance by one party, and for one reaſon, but it may as well be ſo pleaded by any other party, and for any other reaſon. For inſtance, why may not a <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz — <hi>becauſe they help not the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty,</hi> be pleaded by a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as well as any other: Since each may, as indeed each do, ſpeak them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the people of God, and their cauſe the cauſe of the Lord, and thoſe they oppoſe the mighty, and then full cry Curſe all, that do not help them againſt 'em?</p>
            <p>The very reaſon indeed of ſuch diſtinctions and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, muſt be fetched from humor, intereſt, or ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which make every party willing to be a Rebel it ſelf, but denyes that freedom to any other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All the behaviour of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Governours, are but fair leſſons of obedience for us to learn and practiſe. Chriſt taught us to give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> he paid Tribute and Cuſtomes himſelf, he was obedient before the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Jews, before an Heathen <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:109621:9"/>
and that even unto death. The Apoſtles taught obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience not only by precept, but example too: <hi>Paul</hi> appealed to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> whereby he owned that power, though Heathen, and perſecuting too: they were perſecuted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all places, ſcourged, impriſoned, and killed, and yet never medled with Civil Governours, or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: never ſpoke evil of Authority, nor did any thing, that tended to the working in men low and cheap thoughts of them. But contrariwiſe, taught us to <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King:</hi> and to be ſubject not only for wrath, or fear, but even for <hi>Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore all the arguments for reſiſtance drawn from the Glory of God, and propagation of the Goſpel, are falſe, and unchriſtian. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Practices contrary to the commands of God, and example of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, cannot be for the glory of God. Nor can ſins againſt the Goſpel tend to the propagation of the Goſpel. But they that teach ſuch things, are like thoſe in Rom. 2.23. <hi>who make their boaſt of the Law, but through breaking the Law, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Such things are againſt the very nature of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, which is peaceable, and quiet: therefore the Prophet <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7.6, 7, 8, 9. tells us that under the Goſpel the <hi>Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard lye down with the Kid: the Cow and the Bear ſhall feed —and the Lyon eat ſtraw like an Ox: they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain.</hi> By which is meant, all the beſtial qualities of men, whereby they devour, and deſtroy one another, ſhould be changed into meek and gentle tempers. Therefore thoſe, that are not thus transformed from evil to good, from rough and cruel, to kind and gentle, are no true ſubjects of Chriſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom here, they are nominal, but no real Chriſtians.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109621:10"/>
Therefore <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerved that while all the precepts of Philoſophy had but little influence on the minds of men, wherever the Goſpel was really received by any, it made ſuch viſible alterations as of luſtful it made them chaſt and continent; of covetous, kind, and liberal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they were hardly known to be the ſame perſons. This is to become indeed a new Creature: and where men are not ſo, but remain quarrelſome, ungovernable, and upon diſtaſte, and croſs Providences fly to the Pike and Muſquet, it is plain that the Goſpel of peace hath not had its work and effect upon them.</p>
            <p>And we find our Saviour taught us rather to ſuffer wrong, than to right our ſelves by much noiſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance: Matt. 5.39, 40, 41. <hi>Reſiſt not evil: but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other alſo. If any man ſue thee at the Law, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo. And whoſoever ſhall compel thee to go a mile, go with him twain.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 13.35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another.</hi> Theſe were the ancient marks of Chriſtianity, and not Drums, and weapons of War: Chriſtians then gave one another a kiſs of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not reproofs on the point of the Sword. It was ſaid by the Gentiles in the time of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> See how the Chriſtians love one another! Not, as in theſe dayes, Behold how they ſlaughter and deſtroy! Therefore though our Saviour's rules, and precepts, are ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſuited to the prophecies of the Goſpel State, yet the Jews ſeeing ſo much of diviſion, enmity, evil ſpeaking, cenſoriouſneſs, unrulineſs, oppoſitions, wars, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, among them that are called Chriſtians, are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily prejudiced, and hardned in their unbelief, looking for a Meſſias, who ſhall bring into the World ſuch times of peace and love, that <hi>Swords ſhall be beaten into Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109621:10"/>
and Spears into pruning hooks.</hi> Nor will conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Chriſtians believe, that the ſpirit of meekneſs, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> delights in Alarms of War Therefore though the Devil carries on many great actions as an Angel of light, hiding ſin under the gilt of religious pretences, as revenge under colours of Juſtice, cruelty under zeal, rebellion for propagation of the Goſpel, and ruining of Families and Countries for the Glory of God: yet nothing is a greater diſhonour to God, reproach to Chriſtians, or hindrance to the Goſpel; nothing makes more A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, infidels, and looſe profeſſors, than for the ſtricteſt pretenders, and mighty zealots, who would be thought the only Chriſtians, to act contrary to the very nature and deſign of the Goſpel, as this is one, To kill, inſtead of loving one another. To reſiſt, inſtead of ſubmitting to the powers. To contemn and act in deſpight of, inſtead of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to, every Ordinance of man. To make Songs, Libels, and invent all manner of evil on, and againſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of not ſpeaking evil of our Rulers. It was anciently obſerved that the glory of God was more advanced, the Goſpel more propagated, and the number of believers more increaſed by ſufferings, than Arms: whence that ancient, and common ſaying, The blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs is the ſeed of the Church. It was three hundred years after Chriſt before the Chriſtians uſed any Armes, unleſs in the ſervice of the Emperour, who was, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe three Centuries, a Gentile, unleſs charity will allow a plea for <hi>Philip.</hi> But all that while the Sword of the Lord was not in the hand of <hi>Gideon,</hi> but in the mouths of his Prophets: and yet then the Church enlarged her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and gained upon the Gentile World in ſuch wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meaſures, that ſome perſecutions were raiſed purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtop its farther progreſs, leſt of a ſuddain the whole World ſhould become Chriſtian. But when the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109621:11"/>
cut a way for the Goſpel into <hi>America</hi> with the ſword, and ſeeking to conquer Soul and body at once, taught them by the mouth both of their Prieſt, and the Cannon, though they boaſt of the numbers baptized, yet I fear, ſcarce one became Chriſtian any farther than in name; ſince they preſently flew off, and would endure neither the perſons that acted, nor the Religion that ſuffered, ſuch ſlaughters amongſt them. The ſoft breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and whiſpers of the Spirit, are ſoon drowned by the thundrings of Drums.</p>
            <p>Later ages have experienced the ſame truth, for the patient ſufferings of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> under Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> increaſed the number of <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and God ſoon remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the rod, and rewarded the Faith and patience of the Church with more outward proſperity, and greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel, than ever was in this Nation before, or ſince. But when in the time of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the I. men made the Pike and Muſquet the weapons of their warfare, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Sword of the Spirit, and the Shield of Faith; when they pleaded they had more wit than to burn in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> calling the Martyrs Fools, as ſome have done <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe, when called of God, he left his own Country, not knowing whither he went; the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion immediately ſuffered her decayes, and that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, which drew the eyes of all Chriſtendom upon it, hath ever ſince been in the wane, till now it is almoſt loſt in the Fogs and miſt of opinion and diſputes. And the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> is become like another <hi>Babel,</hi> wherein there be almoſt as many Tongues as men, who, inſtead of brick and Lime to raiſe the work, bring axes and hammers to beat it down.</p>
            <p>Which together with mens falling from one error to another, and dancing all the rounds of opinion, and ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at laſt into levelling principles; to own no governour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109621:11"/>
but King Jeſus; that dominion is founded in grace, and that therefore the Sts. ſhall rule the earth, and take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſpoils of the wicked: which are tenents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of all Government, both in Church and State: we may judge a curſe upon the new methods, that men have taken, whereby to ſecure Religion amongſt them.</p>
            <p>The Pope was the firſt that ever preached this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of non-allegiance of Subjects, it was therefore from <hi>Rome</hi> that ſome Proteſtants took theſe meaſures: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently this is more truly Popery, than a Croſs in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and ſuch other things that have not like the other any intrinſick evil in them, and were in the Church long before the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> claimed the title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi> We may therefore ſay of ſuch, while they damn the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for plots, and evil intendments on Governours and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> Rom. 2.3. <hi>Thinkeſt thou this, O man, that judgeſt thoſe that do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Search into all Religions in the World, and perhaps you ſhall find no other but the Alchoran, that ſeeks its propagation by the Sword. For which very thing as well as others, it hath been condemned by all honeſt and judicious men. And doubtleſs without being cenſorious, we may ſay it is <hi>ſelf,</hi> and <hi>not the things of God,</hi> that is ſought in ſuch wayes.</p>
            <p>Now if intereſt cannot perſwade, nor the Goſpel teach, I am ſure our Laws cannot allow ſuch a reſiſtance, which is the</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thing, ſome may think to juſtifie ſuch practices by. For our Laws make all reſiſtance a capital crime; without any limits, or exception; if it be not ſo, let anyone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce but any one ſingle Act, or any clauſe therein, that allows ſuch proceedings. And whereas ſome plead we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109621:12"/>
ought to be governed in ſuch and ſuch wayes, that Kings are not abſolute by the conſtitution of our Government, theſe pleas do not reach the point. For in caſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours do not rule according to Law, but beſide or againſt them, Governours are accountable to God only, but not to their Subjects, who are taught only to obey, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. And I preſume that no man is ſo daring, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his argumentation, as to undertake to make out, that in the firſt conſtitution Subjects have any power of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance upon any account whatſoever. And I doubt not but that the wiſdom and loyalty of Parliaments will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the ſame ſentiments themſelves</p>
            <p>I would fain know, whether ſuch reachings, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes of reſtleſs and unbridled Nature, do not drive at the ſame thing, that our Saviour charged as a very heinous ſin upon the Phariſees, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.13. that they <hi>made the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God of none effect by their traditions.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which properly ſignifies to weaken or ſpoil of its authority, or obligatory power: which is done by pleading any humane conſtitution, tradition, or cuſtom, againſt the Laws and Commands of God: by which means the matter is brought to this point, <hi>Whom ſhall we obey, God or man?</hi> The thing is clear in the inſtance our Saviour gives. The Phariſees by their <hi>Corban,</hi> which was an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Doctrine of ſubtile and covetous Hypocrites, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved children from honouring their indigent Parents with neceſſary ſupplies of food and ſuſtenance: ſo ſuch men by ſuch pleadings of our Laws, would acquit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from the great obligation of honouring their Father (by which, even <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Writers, Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, underſtand not only natural Parents, but Kings) with the natural and indiſpenſable duties of <hi>tribute, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, fear</hi> and <hi>honour, Rom.</hi> 13.7. We may yet further obſerve, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> had really ſuch a Tradition, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109621:12"/>
our Saviour there overthrows: but we have no ſuch Law, therefore theſe Pleas run upon a falſe preſumption, and have no foundation, and therefore are falſe in themſelves, and need not the authority of a Divine command to the contrary, to put them to ſhame and ſilence.</p>
            <p>I wiſh ſuch men would conſider that by ſuch corrupt diſcourſes, they utterly deſtroy that argument, which themſelves are ready enough to uſe, in order to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading Princes to beat out Popery, and to eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Religion in their Dominions, drawn from their own ſafety among Proteſtants, and dangers among Popiſh ſubjects; ſince reſiſtance is favoured, juſtified and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by both. Where was the ſafety of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt among Proteſtants? What is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Ax and Poiſon, or a Piſtol? What is the difference between the Popes abſolving ſome Subjects from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and your teaching, that no Allegeance or duty is owing to ſome Princes? What difference between the Popes diſpoſing of Crowns, and your ſetting up an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? Here is no room for any, unleſs a School diſtinction, which is ſometimes ſo nice, that the difference is not to be found. But you will ſay, that Princes are ſecure enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> when they rule well: but I pray who muſt be Judge of that? Even your own ſelves: and then the meaning is, they are ſafe, while they rule according to your own minds, but not otherwiſe: and ſo much ſafety there is for them amongſt the worſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the World. Therefore reſiſters utterly deſtroy this argument, and loſe the great advantage they might otherwiſe have made of it.</p>
            <p>It is then neither our intereſt, nor duty, nor the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Laws, to make reſiſtance againſt Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109621:13"/>But there are doubtleſs divers motives and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions yet remaining, from which the fondneſs of ſome men, and the ſubtilty of others, raiſe a fancied neceſſity of ſuch proceedings, elſe they think they are all undone, Horſe and Foot; Soul and body: for elſe ſay they, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> will come in; for nothing is now likely to keep it out, but the Sword.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the Heathen Emperours commanded the Chriſtians to deliver up their Bibles, and by confiſcation of Goods, impriſonments, deaths, and all poſſible artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and cruelties, endeavoured to root the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians out of the World; might not they have ſaid, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſtanding on our guards can ſave us? Yet in the time of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> they told the Emperour, that they had Chriſtians in his Armies, in every Town and City, that they wanted not Arms, men nor courage, to defend themſelves from perſecuting hands, yet they dare do no ſuch thing, becauſe their Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus had left them no other weapons but prayers and tears. And what was the iſſue? God carried them through all thoſe fiery Tryals, and increaſed them, as he did the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites of old, under the very means uſed for their extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. It is God that rules over all, and his providence extends to the meaneſt creatures, not a ſparrow falls to the ground without his will: be ſure then that his Church ſhall not be left to the will of his enemies, any further than ſerves the wiſe ends of his providence. The Jews when few and weak, were preſerved in the midſt of a world of enemies: the Chriſtian Church upheld in the boſome of an Heathen Empire; who patiently ſubmitted to all ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and waited milder providences, till he pleaſed <hi>to bring them forth to the light, and ſhew them his righteouſneſs, Mic.</hi> 7.9. Theſe all truſted in God, and were delivered.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109621:13"/>
Why then ſhould we be faithleſs, as if the <hi>Lords arm were ſhortned, that he cannot help us?</hi> This in <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10. is called the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience of the Saints,</hi> that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and would not reſiſt perſecuting Governours. And indeed ſuch reſiſtance moſt plainly evidences the want of Faith, and Patience both: for men firſt doubt God will not deal well by them, and then reſolve, right or wrong, to carve for themſelves. And for this reaſon God is more glorified, and Religion more advanced in unjuſt ſufferings, than in unjuſt reſiſtance, becauſe in ſuch ſufferings men ſhew their <hi>Faith,</hi> their <hi>Hope,</hi> their <hi>Patience, Fortitude,</hi> and other graces, which evidence the excellency of the Chriſtian Religion, by which they wearied and overcame their fierceſt perſecutors: and moreover the wiſdom, goodneſs, and power of God is more clearly ſeen in their preſervation and deliverance, when men <hi>ſit ſtill and ſee the Salvation of God,</hi> than when they ſeek by humane poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſtrength to ſave themſelves: for this ſpeaks both their weakneſs, and derives a reproach upon the Religion they profeſs, and alſo diſpoſes themſelves and others, to attribute what ſafety they have, not ſo much to God as to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The doing evil that good may come on it, never ends well. Where I pray, is all the fruit and gain of the laſt Civil War? What is the Proteſtant Religion the better, or <hi>Proteſtants</hi> the ſafer thereby? Nay what have not both ſuffered ſince then, and (as we may undoubtedly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm) for that very cauſe? For are not the confuſions of our Religion, and the danger of us all (both occaſioned by our preſent differences, and theſe differences occaſioned by that reſiſtance, and the lawleſs liberty it took to it ſelf) greater now than ever? God commonly payes men in their own Coyn. Thus upon the Babyloniſh captivity God told the remains of the people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 42. that in caſe they would continue in their own Land, <hi>he would build,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109621:14"/>
and not pull them down,</hi> v. 10. But if they would go into <hi>Egypt</hi> for fear of the Sword and Famine, which they afterwards did do, then v. 16. <hi>The Sword which you feared, ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you there in the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and the Famine whereof ye were afraid, ſhall follow cloſe after you in</hi> Egypt, <hi>and there ſhall ye dye.</hi> Divine Juſtice overtakes men in their own wayes, and ſnares them in the works of their own hands: making thoſe very courſes whereby they would keep off judgments, to prove their ruine. I am ſure the Jews found it ſo, for <hi>John</hi> 11.48. they plead the neceſſity of crucifying our Saviour in order to the preſervation of themſelves, and their Religion. <hi>If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him, and the Romans will come and take away our place and Nation:</hi> and for that very ſin God brought the Romans upon them, who indeed took away their <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> too. And if theſe things are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our example upon whom the ends of the World are come, we cannot in any reaſon think we may run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe great ſins of Rebellion and murther, which are a breach of ſo many Goſpel precepts, and ſo contrary to the example of Chriſt, and all his Apoſtles, out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ſecure our Religion, but we muſt expect a curſe upon our proceedings. Did men but ſeriouſly conſider, that the laſt war which was pretended purpoſely to keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> proved ſo mighty and ſuddain an inlet to it, that it had almoſt overtaken us, and the reaſons of men cannot think of any thing, which in thoſe circumſtances was like to have kept it off, but his Majeſties reſtoration; they muſt needs ſee the finger of God in that judgment: and own it exactly parallel with the two inſtances juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, unleſs in this only, that it did not proceed to an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine. And if men ſhall uſe the ſame methods, not only condemning things for <hi>Popery</hi> which are not ſo, as the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Church-men, who have done an hundred fold more to confute, and bar out <hi>Popery</hi> than all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109621:14"/>
the parties in <hi>England</hi> beſides can pretend to; but ſhall actually oppoſe the Powers too, which were the two inſtances of the madneſs and error of the late times, I ſhall expect the ſin ſhall breed and bring forth that judgment which they fear, and which ſhall deſtroy the Actors of it. Truth needs not our lie, but abhors it: nor will Religion be ſupported by the hand of ſin, any more than the <hi>wrath of man can work the righteouſneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Some are further confirmed in the perſwaſion that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but reſiſtance can ſave us, from hence, that they ſee but little execution of Laws upon Papiſts.</p>
            <p>I anſwer,</p>
            <p>That it cannot be denyed but that ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have abundantly outdone the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> even in thoſe very things, for which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are condemned. For did the <hi>Papiſts</hi> deſign the murther of the King, and alteration of the Laws and Religion eſtabliſhed? and I pray, did not ſome <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> actually do all this in the memory of thouſands amongſt us, and that in the moſt open and daring methods the world hath ever heard? Yet I can find but ten exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for all thoſe Murthers and Uſurpations, and (which is the complement of all) for the murther of the late King, beyond the example of all ages, and the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this. Look back to <hi>May</hi> 1679. when the Scots moſt barbarouſly butchered Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> their Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; and to the Rebellion, (which it ſeems uſes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Biſhops) that broke out in the ſame month, and their ſtanding a Battle with the Kings Forces; of all whom, and for all which wickedneſs, which is death by the Law, as well as any thing charged upon the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I could never underſtand that above two ſuffered. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as about twenty of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have ſuffered within two years, and three Months laſt paſt. Therefore we may with more truth and reaſon affirm the procedure of the Laws more ſlow againſt <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> than agaiſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109621:15"/>
               <hi>Popiſh</hi> offenders. What reaſon then have ſome <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> to complain of the ſlow paces of Laws in judgment and execution, when themſelves are the greateſt ſharers in the mercy? And if from hence a party ſhould increaſe, and their ſentiments advance the faſter, the advantage is more their own, than thoſe mens whom they complain of. Nor have any among us any cauſe from thence to conclude the inclination of the Powers, either this way or that, but muſt impute it to clemency, and mercy, which hath ever been accounted an admirable qualification of perſons in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and ought to oblige all honeſt, and ingenuous men, to a more free and hearty love, and obedience.</p>
            <p>And that the Lords in the Tower are not yet tryed, is very unjuſtly made a reflection on the King. For there is no man, that knows and conſiders things, but muſt, if truth and honeſty may ſpeak, own that the cauſe is not in him. For no Prince in the World would have left them more freely to juſtice, than the King hath done, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the Parliament that ſat in <hi>October</hi> 1680. For that part of the Speech, which relates to them, ſeems ſomewhat preſſing in this particular: when the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> was tryed, and Sentenced to death, he quickly ſuffered; and that no more of them were tryed at or about the ſame time, was not in any thing that his Majeſty hindred. Therefore, though I do not blame that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who beſt knew the reaſons of their own Actings, yet I muſt in juſtice, and for the cauſe of truth, as well as the better ſatisfaction of the people, argue againſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil ſurmiſe and imputation, that in this affair is caſt upon the King. Men are very ready to ſhoot their bolts, and make every thing they fancy a miſcarriage, to be the <hi>Kings evil,</hi> but when men are told, and their reaſons preſſed upon theſe conſiderations, I cannot hear any one ſo unjuſt to his own faculties, as to maintain the charge againſt his Majeſty. But indeed we that are ſubjects,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109621:15"/>
ſhould ſtudy to be quiet, and mind our own buſineſs, and not meddle with perſons and things above us.</p>
            <p>Though I muſt needs confeſs that ſome reaſons we have no more of ſettlement yet, is rather from the crys and vogue of the people, than from the Policies of the King: For when men will not hear of the Tryal of the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> unleſs they firſt ſee the Biſhops routed: When they deſire not to ſee Popery excluded, unleſs they may firſt ſee the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion laid open by a Liberty, a Toleration of all Sects, perſons and things: When men would not the King ſhould have four penny-worth of Taxes, till he ſhall give away eight penny-worth of Prerogatives: When they would not have <hi>Tangier,</hi> and the Trade of the Nation ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, till the King leave himſelf and friends indefenſible: When they would not have the Papiſts beat down, unleſs they may be made capable of ſetting up themſelves: When every man muſt be a Church-Papiſt, or a Field-Meeter, which is in plain Engliſh a bold Rebel; It is no wonder there be rubs in the way, and a great diſtance between our ſelves, and that ſecurity and ſettlement, we long ſince ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. And that the blame is ſtill laid upon the King, is but the old way to <hi>blacken</hi> his Majeſty, whereby to make men, that have more faith than reaſon, more honeſty than wit or knowledge, to become his enemies.</p>
            <p>It was indeed the ſad fate of the late King, that he was miſ-repreſented by ſome, and miſ-underſtood by others of his Subjects, as a favourer of Popery: but now all men, that will ſee and acknowledge the truth, place him in the rank of true Proteſtants, and the beſt of Kings. And I doubt not, but the Ages to come will acquit his preſent Majeſty from any ſuch imputation, ſince the deſigns upon his Perſon from the Popiſh Party have been ſo many, and ſo deſperate: ſince he hath ſo conſtantly declared for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion, as it is eſtabliſhed by Law:</hi> and ſince he hath done ſo much for the ſecurity and preſervation of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109621:16"/>
ſame; and ſince he hath condeſcended to offer any ſafe and reaſonable expedient for the ſecurity of the fame under a Popiſh Succeſſor, in caſe any ſuch ſhall be. But it is the unhappineſs of moſt men, that they ſee perſons the leaſt, when neareſt them; and underſtand them beſt at farther removes. Which muſt be imputed partly to this, that few know the reaſons of other mens actings, eſpecially while masked and clouded in a multiplicity of affairs and things ariſing from different parties, principles and deſigns; therefore, in ſuch circumſtances, if men judge alwayes according to outward appearance, they muſt needs ſometimes judge amiſs. For the wheels of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſometimes neceſſarily run in the deep, and by many oblique motions, windings, and circumferences, come at laſt to the point they firſt aimed at. Therefore when men alwayes conclude, that their Governours deſign what their faces are at any time ſet towards, they muſt unavoidably fall into error of judgement, and trouble themſelves with needleſs ſuſpicions and fears. And ſometimes the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is founded on want of good information, due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, ſound judgement, and an over-eaſineſs to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined by the unſteady meaſures of fame, which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents perſons and things, not according to their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but according to the raſhneſs, ignorance, ill-will, ſuſpicions, and other unreaſonable humours of men. Theſe indeed are the bitter fountains, from whence our preſent, as well as late fears, jealouſies and unſettlements do ſpring.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many are affrighted into a dreadful expectation of ſome ſevere viſitation by Prodigies: and therefore think it very requiſite to be upon their watch or guard, that they may be ready to receive the ſhock, or rather to ſtave the evil off.</p>
            <p>Indeed there was one prodigious appearance in the face of Heaven in the latter end of <hi>December,</hi> or beginning
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109621:16"/>
of <hi>January</hi> laſt. Things of which nature have formerly been held to be Exhalations kindled in the air; and were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be even operative cauſes of evil: as ſometimes of Famines, the Earth being beggered by ſuch vaſt quantities of ſuch matter drawn from it: ſometimes of Peſtilence, the Air being poiſon'd by noxious matter ariſing from Fens, Bogs, Ditches, Sinks, and other unwholſome places: and ſometimes of War, mens minds being inflamed by I know not what influence from thence, and ſo diſpoſed to quarrels and fighting. But theſe fancies have long ſince been hiſſed off from the Stage. For now moſt men hold, they are no cauſes, but only ſigns and tokens of ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching evils. But theſe conceits have no foundation in Scripture: for though our Saviour foretold ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table appearances, that ſhould precede the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yet this doth not reach our caſe: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That was a calamity, that admitted no parallel; it was a Type of the deſtruction of the world, and was to carry with it ſome ſenſible evidences of Divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, not only againſt that people, but their worſhip, which was at firſt eſtabliſhed by mighty Signs and Wonders.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we are not to expect any like Viſitation, ſo we have no warrant to expect any like prodigies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> threatning a ruine to ſo many Churches, never mentioned any ſuch Sign that ſhould precede that ruine, nor do we elſewhere read of any ſuch thing obſerved to have preceded the ſame; nor doth any Text in the New Teſtament mention any thing of this nature, unleſs in thoſe two caſes, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There were, doubtleſs, ſuch appearances in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, and are thought to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned under the terms of <hi>pillars of fire</hi> and <hi>ſmoak,</hi> yet we no where read, that they ever looked upon them as Signs of the times, as ſome now take it. The <hi>Romans</hi> indeed,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109621:17"/>
and other Nations had very ſacred regards to theſe things long before Chriſt, therefore they ſeem as much of <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> Original, as the <hi>May-poll,</hi> or any thing elſe, that is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned and condemned by ſome amongſt us.</p>
            <p>And if Scripture cannot juſtifie, I am ſure Reaſon hath no plea for any ſuch matter. For the only inducement to ſuch a perſwaſion, is the common obſervation, that they are uſually fore-runners of ſome very ſore viſitation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution. To which we anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes they are owned to be tokens of good, as the birth of Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Many notable changes, and heavy judgements have been in the world, when men have not been alarmed by any Prodigy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Come when they will, ſomething remarkable muſt be expected to follow, becauſe there is little in the world but inſtances of the frailty of nature, and uncertainty of humane affairs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They do not remain fixed, like the Sword over <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> nor do they hover about one Countrey only, as the Armies in the Air about <hi>Judaea,</hi> but paſs over great part of the world. Therefore from theſe heads it unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably follows, that men cannot ſay whether the Prodigy portends</p>
            <p n="1">1. Good, or</p>
            <p n="2">2. Evil, or</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither: that is, whether any thing, or nothing.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it bodes ſome evil, yet no man can tell, whether it be</p>
            <p n="1">1. To us, or</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the Dutch, German, French, Italian, or any other, to whom it hath been as viſible, as here.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it portends ſome evil to us, yet none can gueſs what evil, whether</p>
            <p n="1">1. Any thing from a <hi>Popiſh</hi> hand, or</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109621:17"/>2. Whether it may not be an evil, that ſome men are diſpoſed to run into, in order to keeping out ſome other evil they may fear.</p>
            <p>There is no certain conjecture then from things of this nature; but they have been often abuſed to vanity, or wicked purpoſes: for while they take off mens minds from the more ſteady rules of Scripture, and reaſon, which ſhewmen what they muſt expect from the works that they have done; they have uſually been made an incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to men of all ſides, parties, and cauſes: And have oftentimes affrighted ſome, and incouraged others to thoſe diſturbances, and other evils, they had not elſe been like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have run into. Therefore it hath been the policy of wiſe men of old, obſerving that no good, and many times great evils befel a Society from attendance to, and conjectures from ſuch appearances, to uſe all prudent means they could to take off men from ſuch Vanities. There is as much foundation in reaſon for <hi>Palm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtry, Augury,</hi> and ſuch other Ethnick cuſtomes, as for preſages from monſtrous births, and generations on the Earth, or in the Heavens. And as the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and at laſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> with other Heathen people, were the great obſervers of ſuch things; ſo it was the Nations that lived without God in the world, who gave the firſt being to theſe conceits; for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we may plead, as our Saviour in another caſe, <hi>after theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek:</hi> which would be argument enough againſt it, were it an inſtitution, or rite of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But admit they are ſome general Alarms to mankind, yet that we of this Nation ſhould draw from them certain concluſions of evil upon us, when they paſs over ſo great a part of the World, is an humour like that of the late times, which would have the prophecies of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelations</hi> to be accompliſht in <hi>England</hi> only.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:109621:18"/>But other Prodigies ſo much talked of, and ſtill believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many, there is no truth in them. For the Saddles ſaid to riſe out of the Earth, are now as confidently ſaid to come to nothing. And all the groanings of men, and ſhrieks and cries of women and children, as if under ſome bitter torments, ſaid by a weekly Intelligence about 17. Months ſince, to have been heard at <hi>Edgehil</hi> in <hi>Warwick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> are notoriouſly falſe. What is become of the Army, and the audible reports of Guns, ſaid to have been ſeen and heard at <hi>Hatfield,</hi> ſome time this winter? Where are the Armies reported to have been ſeen in the air in <hi>Leiceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire?</hi> Where is the blazing Star, ſaid to have been viſible ſeveral nights to people about <hi>VVarwickſhire,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? I might give in a long relation of Prodigies, that have had no being, but only the fears, fancies, and mouths of the people. I find a whole heap of ſuch ſtuff raked up together, in a book printed <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1662, or 61. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are told of a Drum beating at certain times in a well in <hi>Oundle</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> and of the waters turned to blood at the time the ſaid Drum was heard, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by fits ſuch a ſpace, that people came many miles, and were frequent witneſſes to thoſe things; but when my ſelf ſome time after inquired of the truth of this relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I found the inhabitants of the place wholly ſtrangers to any ſuch matters. And divers other very monſtrous relations, from which nothing can be learned, but the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, falſhood, and religious frenzies of ſome great zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots. By which wild extravagancies they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men to believe that even Heaven it ſelf gives appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation to their cauſe, that the Stars fight in their courſes for them, that even Nature goes out of her common paths to make way for <hi>them:</hi> that all the Elements, and whole Juries of the creatures, give in their verdicts for them: whence it muſt needs be concluded that they are
<q>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109621:18"/>Chara Dei Soboles—</q>
the <hi>people of God,</hi> and the offspring of Heaven. Though I know no greater evidences of an overgrown hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and pride; yet it is ſtrange how wonderfully thoſe devices take with the people: for whilſt every party are of ſo different intereſts and Religions, yet they all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive theſe things with ſuch religious regards, that they will undertake to ſpell out of them the fall of Princes, the revolution of Government, and the advance every one of his own party, though as inconſiſtent together, as the preſent eſtabliſhment, and themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now whilſt it is made a very heavy charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they uphold their Religion by <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lies,</hi> and <hi>pious frauds:</hi> all parties amongſt us do the very ſame thing. For by theſe ſtratagems men gather, keep and increaſe their parties; for poor well-meaning people ſeldom queſtion the truth of ſuch pretended Prodigies, but receive them as ſigns from Heaven ſent to condemn what they diſlike, and approve what themſelves eſpouſe, and as aſſurances that in little time God will appear for them. Whereas would men ſpeak truth, all thoſe ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parties would ſoon ſhrivel to a little ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>And that we may not be overtaken with the error of the times, and the ſtrong deluſions the Scripture mentions, we ſhould be careful not to make Prodigies the touchſtone, whereby to try the truth of a Religion, the lawfulneſs of a Government, or the goodneſs of a cauſe. Nor ſhould we receive the reports of any Prodigies, till we ſee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient confirmation, and good reaſon to do ſo. By which means we ſhall exclude many of thoſe fears, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may terrifie and diſcompoſe us. For as peoples at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to ſuch things is the greateſt evidence of unſetled minds, and reaching after ſome new thing; ſo it is the ready courſe to hurry men into raſh Counſels, and thoſe precipitant actions, they may afterwards have all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109621:19"/>
in the world to repent. But we ſhould bottom our ſelves upon the beſt foundation, which is a good life, and a clear conſcience from all forbidden things and works of darkneſs, and then we need not be much concerned what colours may be hung out from the battlements of Heaven, but may compoſe ourſelves into a faith and confidence that whatever comes, it ſhall be well with us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not <hi>fear though the Earth be removed, and the mountains caſt into the ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Many men are mightily moved to ſuch ſentiments, <hi>viz.</hi> of the neceſſity of a reſiſtance, by evil reports raiſed on Governours. For while we ſhould <hi>not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of the people, Exod.</hi> 22.28. it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the humor of the times to blaſt their names, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatter all their Actions Were they never ſo vile, this can be no part of our Religion, but is the work of him, who is an accuſer of the brethren: and therefore is called the Devil, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to calumniate, or ſlander. But we may obſerve that all the Actions of Governours are backwards and forwards turned to evil. For while any part of the Army raiſed for <hi>Flanders</hi> were in Arms, they are ſaid to be kept up to ſecure our ruine: when they are all disbanded, the deſign muſt needs be to leave us naked, and expoſed to ſlaughters. This time was two year, there was no Fleet out, the reaſon of which was ſaid to be, that we might lye open to Forreign Invaſions: when the King would have ſet out a Fleet in <hi>April</hi> 1679. the deſign muſt then be to impoveriſh the Nation. Theſe two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may mind the Reader of many others of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from which it is moſt palpably plain, that a Spirit of jealouſie in ſome men, and evil intendments in others, make dangers where they cannot find them; and where there is no Bear nor Lyon in the way, will affright fools with their own ſhadows. But where men know no more than what is told them; and eaſily receive whatever is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109621:19"/>
offered, it is no wonder that the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of pretended Prodigies, and the black repreſentations of Governours and Government, bring them to their wits end; and make them think there is no ſafety left, when the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may be of their own making. It is from hence, that (as I have often obſerved) the ſame times have two faces, the one blear-ey'd and alwayes weeping the other more fair and comely. For go amongſt the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Town, hear their ſtories, and you will think the world is at an end: for you ſhall ſee nothing but Signs in the Sun, and in the Moon, and on earth Goblins and Furies, diſtreſs of Nations, mens hearts failing them for fear, and for looking for the things that are coming on the world; but diſcourſe with men that are more wiſe and obſerving, who fetch their knowledge from the things themſelves, not from the reports and ſentiments of others, and we find a place ſtill left for hope, and a comfortable enjoyment of our ſelves: and what evil circumſtances we are in, we there ſee not only the evil it ſelf, but the true Origin, or cauſe, and therefore can the better compoſe and quiet our ſelves, than under the monſtrous ſhapes and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that are given to men in the dark. Therefore men muſt of neceſſity either better inform themſelves, or not be over credulous in believing others; elſe they ſhall never clear themſelves from this evil, but ſhall alwayes lye harraſſed under falſe fears, and be in danger of taking wrong methods for their own ſafety.</p>
            <p>Before we diſmiſs this Head, it will not be impertinent to obſerve, that though men matter not what they ſay of Authority among men of their own perſwaſion, yet ſome are ſo wary, that when they would impoyſon others, and are not willing their own tongues ſhould paint the King in thoſe ugly colours they would repreſent him in, they have a cunning device of doing it by the tongues of others, <hi>viz.</hi> by little ſtories, as one between the King and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109621:20"/>
Cobler, being this, That the heel of the King's Shooe coming off, he ſteps <hi>incognito</hi> to a Cobler to ſet it on, which done, the Cobler is paid ſo well, that he ſends for Ale to make his Maſter drink: the King drinks the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s health, which the Cobler refuſes for this reaſon, that <hi>he is a Papiſt:</hi> then his Majeſty drinks the King's health, which the Cobler refuſes too, for, ſaith he, <hi>the King is little better.</hi> Which in their canting, looks like a <hi>Meioſis,</hi> whereby more is underſtood, than expreſt. Now becauſe themſelves dare not ſay too openly that the King is a Papiſt, therefore the Cobler is made to do it, and that not as from himſelf, but as ſpeaking the common ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the people: which is the moſt wicked way of ſlandering in the world, becauſe the voice of the people makes a much deeper impreſſion, than a ſingle opinion. The ſtory thus ended, it is pretty to obſerve, that this Cobler is made to follow the King where ever he goes. At firſt this was done at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> then <hi>Windſor,</hi> ſometimes in the way between both, and anon about <hi>Newmarket;</hi> and now at laſt at <hi>Woodſtock.</hi> Nor are the places more, than the times in which it hath been ſaid to be done: For I heard it firſt about two years ſince, yet now it is told afreſh, as if done this <hi>March,</hi> when the Court was at <hi>Oxford.</hi> The ſtory, it ſeems, is like the Cuckow, that comes once in the year, ſings a while till ſhe is hoarſe, and the ſtory ſtale, then lyes ſcab'd a while in a corner, and of a ſuddain comes fluſh't abroad, ſings brisk, and gains the peoples ear, as if it were ſome new tale ſhe tells.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the great diſturbers of our peace, and the Thieves that rob us of our our beſt Jewels, in a quiet and a ſetled mind. And whilſt they talk of want of Trade, themſelves by ſuch courſes hinder it: it being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of men, firſt to make an evil, and then charge it upon Authority; <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> being made the <hi>Scape-goats,</hi> to bear the peoples ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109621:20"/>As there would not be many Thieves, were there no Receivers: ſo the mouth of wickedneſs would not be ſo open, were mens ears ſtopt againſt their evil whiſpers. Therefore the beſt expedient both to compoſe our minds, and to check this ſpreading leproſie, is to follow <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice, Prov. 24.21. <hi>My ſon, fear thou the Lord, and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, men of hot heads, or deſperate fortunes, or ſuch as have fed on Crown and Church-lands (the ſin truly lying in thoſe eſtates, not in the perſons) may reach this way. But the people under a reſiſtance, are like to prove the miſerable hands, that ſhall only miniſter to the ambition and intereſt of others. For what gains can you expect, but hard marches, hungry bellies, field quarters, frequent alarms, bloody battels, wounds, and death?</p>
            <q>Haec ſpolia noſtra!</q>
            <p>If you come off with life, loſs of limbs, ſcars, pains, aches and poverty, are like to be all your trophies! For when the Parliament Army broke up, the main Body being by Arms put out of a way to live, ſome returned Shabs to their own Countreys, others ſought for death in foreign Service, and ſome turning Robbers, took up their laſt Quarters at the Gallows. Therefore though you may hear fine ſtories of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the Pleas of Rebellion, 'twas ſo in the matter of <hi>Corah,</hi> 'twas ſo lately with us, and ſo with <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who in the end only purchaſed a Kingdom by his Souldiers blood; yet it is good for men to conſult their own ſafety, <hi>and not run out of Gods bleſſing into the warm Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
